Guide to the New-York Historical Society Manuscripts of Lectures and Addresses 1809-1957, 2001, 2015-2016 NYHS-RG 11
New-York Historical Society
- [George H. Moore, copyist]. [Letters of Jo. Clark Etc.], 1869 February 2 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Includes transcriptions of letters of the 1670s to and from Silvester Salisbury, Governor of Fort Albany. The minutes of the N-YHS meeting of 2 February 1869 indicate that George H. Moore read one of these letters, that of Jo. Clark to Salisbury.
- George C. McWhorter. Biographical Sketch of the Life of John Lawrance, 1869 February (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Includes 2 versions. According to one of the documents, one is the February text read by George H. Moore to N-YHS on 15 May 1869, and the second is a revised version, apparently also from 1869, received by N-YHS on 5 January 1886.
- Henry C. Van Schaack. Alderman Benson's Memoir of the Benson Family, with an Introduction and Additional Paper in Reference to Judge Egbert Benson, 1869 April 6 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- William F. Morgan, D.D. Conservatism and Its Relation to Progress, 1869 November (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Includes two manuscript copies of this anniversary address.
- [Unidentified]. [Trends in American Aboriginal History], [Circa 1870?] (Box 3, Folder 18)
- William P. Prentice. A Historical Sketch of the Courts of New York, 1870 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  In addition to the paper, the folder includes two letters from Prentice, including his transmittal to George Moore of the paper.
- [Benson J. Lossing]. [Memorial for Alexander Anderson, the First Engraver on Wood in America], [1870 October 5] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  In addition to Lossing's text, there is a letter from Evert A. Duyckinck to Lossing about Anderson, which was read by Lossing as part of his remarks.
- [Horace Greeley]. The American Desert, [1870 December 6] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Includes notes of Greeley's address, on 22 slips of paper.
- George C. McWhorter. An Incident in the War Between the United States and Mexico, [1872 May 7] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Read by George H. Moore at the N-YHS meeting of 7 May.
- Isaac J. Greenwood. The Samuel Maverick Lot of 1669 on Broadway, 1873 February 22 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- [George Washington Greene]. German Troops in the War of Independence, [1873 June 3] (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Read by George H. Moore at the N-YHS meeting of 3 June.
- [John Austin Stevens]. [Memorial of] George Gibbs, [1873 October 7] (Box 4, Folder 6)
- [James C. Welling]. [Mecklenburg County Declaration of Independence of 1775], [1874 February 3] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Includes Welling's address and two manuscript copies of remarks that appear to have been delivered in response to Welling's address. These remarks were likely those of either Joseph B. Varnum or Erastus C. Benedict; according to the minutes of the meeting, both made comments in connection with making a motion for a resolution of thanks to Welling.
- John Austin Stevens. The Progress of New York in a Century, 1776-1876, 1875 December 7 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  See also the set of folders below for related material: [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?].
- George Bancroft. The Place in History of Washington's Letter of March 1781 to Pendleton, Wythe and Jefferson of Virginia, [1876 March 7] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Includes Bancroft's paper, with letters of December 1875 to George Moore transmitting the paper, and the meeting announcement.
- [George H. Moore]. Memorial of Life of Thomas Barron, Deceased, [1876 March 7] (Box 4, Folder 10)
  In addition to the text of the memorial, there is a clipping of the obituary of Barron from the New York Evening Post of 6 September 1875 and a transcript of the obituary.
- John Austin Stevens. The New-York Delegation to the Continental Congress, 1774-1776, 1876 April 4 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  The paper was read twice, on 4 April 1876 and on 2 May 1876.
- [Charles O'Conor]. [The Constitutions], [1877 May 8] (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Lecture given as part of the celebration of the 100th anniversary of the adoption of the New York State Constitution, held at the Academy of Music. In addition to the address, the folder includes an admission ticket to the event.
- George W.W. Houghton. The Last British Commander at New-York: Sir Guy Carleton, 1881 November 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- [William Beach Lawrence]. Albert Gallatin (1 of 3), [1882 February 7] (Box 4, Folder 14)
  The paper was read by Edward F. de Lancey at the February 1882 N-YHS meeting. This set of folders includes two manuscript copies of the address, one of which appears to be incomplete, research notes, and the 1880 letter from Secretary of the Executive Committee Jacob Moore requesting Lawrence to deliver the address on the occasion of N-YHS's 76th anniversary in that year.
- [William Beach Lawrence]. Albert Gallatin (2 of 3), [1882 February 7] (Box 4, Folder 15)
- [William Beach Lawrence]. Albert Gallatin (3 of 3), 1880-1882 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Orsamus H. Marshall. Expedition of the Sieur de Champlain Against the Onondagas in 1615., 1885 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Includes two typescripts (one incomplete) that were advance sheets for an edition of Marshall's writings published by Joel Munsell's Sons, dated 1885 on the sheets. The sheets indicate that the original paper was sent to N-YHS in October 1875, which is confirmed by the meeting minutes of 5 October 1875, though it does not appear to have been read then. See also Marshall's paper on the same subject above in 1849.
- Harman C. Westervelt. Early Colonial Dutch Churches, 1885 December 22 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Includes Westervelt's paper and his transmittal letter of it to Recording Secretary Andrew Warner. Also includes Westervelt's 8 January 1886 letter to Domestic Corresponding Secretary Edward de Lancey concerning Westervelt's attribution to John Milton Bennett of the alliteration "Seige of Belgrade."
- Rocellus S. Guernsey. New York City in the War of 1812-15 (1 of 2), [1888 March 6] (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Includes pages 1-150 and the meeting announcement.
- Rocellus S. Guernsey. New York City in the War of 1812-15 (2 of 2), 1888 March 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Includes pages 151-264, with unnumbered pages at the end.
- John Austin Stevens. The Merchants of New York in 1789, 1889 May 7 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Albert Ross Parsons. New Light Upon the Immemorial Antiquity of the Name of America and the Significance of the Arms of the United States, 1893 May 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Includes Parsons's printed map inserted at the back of his paper that illustrates his point regarding the linkage between constellations and geographic names and national symbols.
- Isaac J. Greenwood. Early Equestrian Performances in Europe and America, 1893 November 7 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  In addition to Greenwood's paper, there are 11 engravings likely used as illustrations in connection with his address.
- Monsignor [Robert] Seton, D.D. [The First Episcopal See of America], 1895 February 5 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  In addition to Seton's paper, the folder includes the meeting announcement.
- Dr. Paul Richard Brown. [Paul Richard (1697-1756), 29th Mayor of New York City], [1896 February 4] (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Includes a photostat copy taken by N-YHS in 1939 of a privately-owned typescript "History and Genealogy of the Richard Family."
- Ellen Hardin Walworth. Robert R. Livingston in the Revolutionary War, 1896 March 5 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Monsignor [Robert] Seton, D.D. An American Traveler in Egypt, 1898 February 1 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Daniel Van Pelt. The Borough of Manhattan, 1899 March 7 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Paper read by A. Emerson Palmer. Includes Van Pelt's paper, his transmittal letter to Librarian William Kelby, and the meeting announcement card.
- Henry R. Stiles. The Borough of Brooklyn, 1899 April 4 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Includes Stiles's paper, his transmittal letter to William Kelby, and the meeting announcement card.
- William F. Wyckoff. The Borough of Queens, 1899 May 2 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Ira K. Morris. The Borough of Richmond, 1899 June 6 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Includes Morris's paper and the meeting announcement. The folder also includes a color advertisement (cut in half) on heavy stock paper for the 1900 New York World Almanac.
- Frederic Wendell Jackson. The Borough of the Bronx, 1899 October 3 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Includes Jackson's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Sidney H. Carney, Jr., M.D. The New York Medical Profession in 1800, 1900 February 3 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  Includes Carney's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Edward L. Tilton. New York Architecture in the Past Century, 1900 March 6 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  Includes Tilton's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Francis W. Halsey. Journalism in New York City in 1800, 1900 April 3 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Includes Halsey's paper and the meeting announcement. Halsey is identified as the editor of the New York Times Saturday Review.
- [John Austin Stevens]. Progress of New York in a Century, 1800-1900 (1 of 2), [1900 May 1] (Box 6, Folder 1)
- [John Austin Stevens]. Progress of New York in a Century, 1800-1900 (2 of 2), [1900 May 1] (Box 6, Folder 2)
- [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?] (1 of 5), circa 1899-1901 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  This set of five folders includes what appears to be research notes and other documents compiled by John Austin Stevens and/or William Kelby for Stevens. The first four folders appear to relate to Stevens's Progress of New York, and there are some letters here from 1901 concerning the possible publication of that work. The last folder concerns commemorations of the dates of George Washington's birth and death. These documents were found boxed together. Although nothing else explicitly links all of the documents together, most of them were tri-folded together in small packets. Sheets originally tri-folded together were kept together in paper slings in each folder.
- [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?] (2 of 5), circa 1899-1901 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?] (3 of 5), circa 1899-1901 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?] (4 of 5), circa 1899-1901 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?] (5 of 5), circa 1899-1901 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- [Asa Bird Gardiner].The Bench and Bar of the City of New York During the 19th Century, [1900 October 2] (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Frank Warren Crane. New York Amusements in 1800, 1900 November 7 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Includes Crane's paper and the meeting announcement.
- William S. Pelletreau. The Days of the Stage Coach, or Travel To and From This City in 1800, 1900 December 4 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  Includes Pelletreau's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Francis W. Halsey. The Indians of New York and Their Famous League, 1901 March 5 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  Halsey is identified as the editor of the New York Times Saturday Review.
- Randall Comfort. Colonial Homes in the Bronx, 1901 November 6 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  Includes Comfort's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Frank Warren Crane. History and Humor in Colonial Advertisements, 1902 March 4 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- [Thomas J. Burton]. Greenwich Village and Landmarks in its Vicinity, [1903 October 6] (Box 6, Folder 14)
  Includes two manuscript copies, including a rough draft, the meeting announcement, and a published article by Burton on the subject (1894?). Burton gave the talk again on 4 April 1904 to another audience at the University Place Presbyterian Church; the card announcing that lecture, with an engraved illustration, is also in the folder.
- [William S. Pelletreau]. The Village of Chelsea and Its Surroundings, [1903 November 4] (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Includes Pelletreau's address, the meeting announcement, a list of negatives acquired by Pelletreau for his stereopticon talk, notes that might be talking points related to the lantern slides used, and a typescript of a 1750 indenture between members of the Somerindyck and Egbert Hereman families and Thomas Clarke (all of New York).
- Frank Warren Crane. Yorkville (Yorkville Village and its Landmarks), [1903 December 1] (Box 7, Folder 2)
- [Francis W. Leggett]. New Harlem (The Village of Harlem and its Environs), [1904 February 2] (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Includes Leggett's talk with references in the text numbered to relate to the included list of slides used in the stereopticon presentation. Also included is the meeting announcement and genealogical notes on Jacob Smith (b. 1817) and the Chesterman family.
- [Hopper Striker Mott]. The Bloomingdale District, [1904 March 1] (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Includes Mott's talk with references in the text numbered to relate to the included list of slides and captions used in the stereopticon presentation, and the meeting announcement. Also included is a separate document titled "The Bloomingdale Road, From a Historical and Legal Viewpoint" intended as a chapter of "The Bloomingdale District." The pages of "Bloomingdale Road" are pasted into the right (credit) side of an account book for the period January-March 1875 maintained by an unidentified individual. The debit accounts on the left are still readable, though Mott's annotations on his text are also on those pages; the credit accounts can be discerned with some difficulty.
- Reginald Pelham Bolton. Fort Washington and Vicinity, [1904 April 5] (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Includes Bolton's address, the transmittal letter to Librarian Robert Kelby, and the meeting announcement.
- Edward Hagaman Hall. Fort Amsterdam & Its Successors, 1904 May 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Includes Hall's address, the transmittal letter to Librarian Robert Kelby, and the meeting announcement.
- Clarence Storm. Burton's Views of New York, 1830, 1904 June 7 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  Includes two copies of the address and the meeting announcement. See also the set of folders below for related material: [Clarence Storm]. [Research Notes].
- [Frank Warren Crane]. [City Hall Park and Vicinity], [1904 October 4] (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Robert Hendre Kelby. The New York Historical Society: A Retrospect, 1904 November 1 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  Includes Kelby's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Report of Speeches at the Dinner of the New York Historical Society, Delmonico's [Centennial Anniversary] (1 of 2), 1904 November 22 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  This folder and the next includes drafts of the report of the speeches given at the banquet. It also includes the banquet program. The folder also includes the text and list of slides for Reginald Pelham Bolton's talk "Indian Life in the Great Metropolis" although this does not appear to be related to the anniversary banquet.
- Report of Speeches at the Dinner of the New York Historical Society, Delmonico's [Centennial Anniversary] (2 of 2), 1904 November 22 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Rocellus S. Guernsey. New York City During the War of 1812, 1904 December 6 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  Read by Robert Kelby as an introduction to Guernsey's stereopticon presentation (not included). Includes two manuscript copies of Guernsey's paper and the meeting announcement.
- Oswald Garrison Villard, A.M.. The Early History of Wall Street, 1653-1789, [1905 May 2] (Box 7, Folder 13)
  Includes Villard's paper and the meeting announcement.
- [Hopper Striker Mott]. Madison Square and Vicinage, 1905 June 6 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Includes Mott's address in a notebook that also includes Mott's references, notes, two letters (1907), and clippings to 1909. Also included is a typescript version and the meeting announcement.
- [William S. Pelletreau.] Union Square and Its History, [1905 October 3] (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Includes Pelletreau's address, the list of associated stereopticon views, the meeting announcement, a 1911 letter from the New York City Parks Department to Robert Kelby regarding the removal of railings formerly enclosing Madison and Union Squares, and a photocopy of a 1985 New York Times article about Union Square.
- Thomas J. Burton. Washington Square, [1905 November 8] (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Includes Burton's paper and the meeting announcement.
- [Clarence Storm]. Bowling Green and its Vicinity (1 of 2), [1906 October 2] (Box 8, Folder 4)
  This folder and the next includes multiple copies, drafts, and notes of Storm's paper. The folder also includes multiple copies of undated addresses on Old New York made by Storm to the Sons of the Revolution, St. Nicholas Club and the Colonial Order. See also the set of folders below for related material: [Clarence Storm]. [Research Notes].
- [Clarence Storm]. Bowling Green and its Vicinity (2 of 2), [circa 1906] (Box 8, Folder 5)
- [Clarence Storm]. [Research Notes] (1 of 2), circa 1904-1914 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  These two folders include clippings, correspondence, images (engravings, postcards), a map of lower Manhattan distributed by a realtor as a marketing piece, and other documents that appear to have been compiled in connection with Storm's research for his talks on old New York.
- [Clarence Storm]. [Research Notes] (2 of 2), circa 1904-1914 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- John Austin Stevens. Physical Development of the City of New York (On the Plan of the Commissioners): A Centennial Contrast, 1807-1907. Clarence Storm. [Introductory Remarks], 1907 April 2 and May 7 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Stevens's paper was read by Robert Kelby at the 2 April 1907 meeting and by Clarence Storm at the 7 May 1907 meeting. Includes a draft and final text of Stevens's paper, his transmittal of it to Kelby, the 2 April meeting announcement, and Storm's introductory comments to his reading of the paper. See also the set of folders above for possibly related material: [John Austin Stevens?]. [Research Notes?].
- Edward Hagaman Hall. [Robert Fulton and Steam Navigation], 1907 October 1 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  Includes Hall's address, an appendix with citations sent the following month to Robert Kelby, Hall's request of Kelby for his assistance in acquiring photographic images from the Robert Fulton Monument Association for his slide presentation, and the meeting announcement. The announcement indicates that the meeting will be in the Hall of N-YHS's new building on Central Park West so this is possibly the first paper read there.
- [Clarence Storm]. [Powder Horns of the French and Indian War and the War of the Revolution], [1909 June 1] (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Includes multiple drafts and versions of Storm's paper on powder horns. He spoke on the topic to at least two organizations other than N-YHS: the Society of Colonial Wars and the Sons of the Revolution. Each presentation varied apparently in different time periods covered (colonial or Revolutionary). All the presentations are in the folder, though there appears to be some confusion in the paging. The stereopticon illustrations used were from N-YHS's Isaac J. Greenwood collection of watercolors. The folder also includes the newspaper The Sun for 20 June 1909, with an article on powder horns on page 8.
- Mrs. A.T. [Alice Crary] Sutcliffe. Robert Fulton, the Man, [1909 November 9] (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Dr. H. T. [Herman Theodoor] Colenbrander. [Holland as a Colonizing Power], 1910 January 11 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Read at N-YHS before both N-YHS and the Holland Society of New York.
- J. W. Rutherford. Progress of Transportation in New York City, Etc., 1910 May 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Robert Hendre Kelby. New York in the Pre-Revolutionary Period, 1765-1774, 1910 November 1; 1913 December 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Read by Kelby on both dates. In addition to Kelby's paper, the folder includes what appears to be an original clipping from a circa 1773 newspaper, with annotations. The clipping is a table titled "An exact account of the number of inhabitants of the city and county of New-York, as appears by the returns of the several constables of the said city and county," annotated to be as of October 1770.
- Robert Hendre Kelby. New York During the Revolution, 1912 April 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- William Henry Shelton. Washington at the Morris House (Roger Morris House of the Revolution), 1912 May 7 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- [Clarence Storm]. Old New York Fires and Fire Laddies, [1912 December 3] (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Includes multiple copies of the paper, drafts, clippings, and notes.
- Robert Hendre Kelby. New York After the Revolution, 1783-1789, 1917 April 3 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Everett P. Wheeler. Daniel Webster: Lawgiver and Statesman, 1918 January 8 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Worthington C. Ford. [The Importance of Personal Papers and Diaries for Research into New York History], 1922 January 3 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Winthrop P. Tryon. How John Jay Kept New York From Going Tory, 1923 March 6 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Dixon Ryan Fox. [The New England Puritans], 1923 November 20 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  Includes a typescript taken by Master Reporting Service of Dixon's address and N-YHS President John A. Weekes's introductory and concluding remarks, on the occasion of N-YHS's 119th anniversary. A second copy of the typescript includes edits to Weekes's remarks.
- Speeches Delivered at Reception Tendered to Mr. Isaac Newton Phelps Stokes, 1925 November 17 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  Includes three addresses on New York history: Alexander C. Flick (New York State Historian), "The Dutch Period"; John H. Finley (Editor, New York Times), "The English Period"; and Robert E. Dowling (President, City Investing Company), "The American Period."
- Poultney Bigelow. John Bigelow and How He Prevented Napoleon III from Assisting Jefferson Davis During the Great Civil War, [1931 December 1] (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Includes Bigelow's address and a photograph of a monument to John Bigelow at Malden on Hudson.
- Leon Dabo. Presentation of the New York Historical Society's Gold Medal to Mr. DeWitt McClellan Lockman, 1933 November 20 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Includes a typescript of portions of the N-YHS meeting commemorating its 129th anniversary and at which Lockman received N-YHS's gold medal. The bulk of the document includes Dabo's comments, which concern the underappreciation of American artists by Americans and Europeans. The remainder of the document includes Executive Committee Chairman Robert E. Dowling's introductory and concluding remarks.
- Nicholas Murray Butler. Dedication Ceremonies, 1939 March 30 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Includes a typescript taken by the State Law Reporting Company of portions of the dedication ceremony for the newly-expanded N-YHS building on Central Park West. The bulk of the document includes Butler's address, which concerns the importance of studying history, continuing revelations in the study of New York's history, and the importance of N-YHS in historical inquiry.The document also includes the introductory and concluding remarks of First Vice-President R. Horace Gallatin.
- Alexander J. Wall, Jr. How St. Nicholas Became Santa Claus, [1939 December 6] (Box 10, Folder 4)
- [Marian Sadtler Hornor]. St. Nicholas Came to New York, [1941 December 15] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Includes Hornor's address and the program for the related Christmas event.
- Carl Van Doren. [The Daily Life of the Continental Army], 1945 February 13 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  Includes two typescripts, with edits, of Van Doren's address taken by the Stenotype Reporting Company at the opening of N-YHS's exhibition Our G.I.'s in Seven Wars. The typescript also includes the introductory and concluding remarks of Director R.W.G. Vail. The typescript is marked by Vail as being restricted from publication.
- Major General Orlando Ward. Possible and Practical Use of Military History, 1952 March 4 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  Includes Ward's address given in connection with a new military gallery and special exhibition at N-YHS commemorating the 150th anniversary of West Point and the brochure for the lecture event.
- Sigmund Spaeth. New York's History in Song., 1953 June 8 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  Appears to be an outline of Spaeth's survey of New York-related songs (3 copies).
- Allan Nevins. The Golden Thread in the History of New York, 1954 November 16 (Box 10, Folder 9)